Roberta Rocca, PhD

Who am I?

Hi there! I am a researcher working at the intersection between cognitive science, NLP, and informatics, with experience in both European and US research institutions and several publications in high-impact scientific journals. My research focuses on applying machine learning techniques to study human language and cognition, on developing open-source software for reproducible neuroscience, and on using NLP for language-based psychiatric assessment. I thrive in teams with ambitious interdisciplinary research agendas and when working on projects with a strong focus on real-world impact.



Skills

Programming languages: Python; SQL; R; Matlab; bash; PERL
Main libraries, frameworks and tools: TF/Keras; PyTorch; Scikit-learn; numpy/scipy; pandas; Git; Docker
Areas of Expertise: ML/NLP; Language; Cognition; Statistical Modeling; Experimental methods; Open Science
Languages: Italian (native); English (fluent); Danish (fluent); French (intermediate)

Experience

Postdoctoral Researcher

December 2020 - ongoing

School of Culture and Society, Aarhus University, Denmark

 $Focus\ areas: \ {\tt Natural\ Language\ Processing,\ Machine\ Learning\ for\ Health,\ Computational\ Social\ Science} \\ \textit{Key\ achievements}$

- Engineered and evaluated text- and audio-based ML models for psychiatric diagnostics
- Created and analyzed multilingual datasets of social media text through APIs and ML pipelines
- Developed methodologies for large-scale semantic modeling of multilingual text data
- Coordinated online survey-based data collection for an international social science consortium \underline{Note} : This role was a part-time collaboration between 12/2020 and 4/2022 (hence the overlap with my employment at UT Austin), and became full-time after that.

Postdoctoral Researcher

December 2019 - April 2022

Psychoinformatics Lab, University of Texas at Austin, USA

Focus areas: Neuroinformatics, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing Key achievements

- Co-developed Neuroscout, an open-source Python platform for end-to-end analysis of brain imaging data
 - lacktriangle Developed and maintained the feature extraction library $\underline{\text{pliers}}$
 - Authored <u>Neuroscout's release paper</u> and its <u>open code repository</u>
 - Performed QA-testing and contributed to Neuroscout's documentation
- Engineered and trained transformers for text-based user encoding and context-aware language modeling
- Conducted research on model evaluation across machine learning and cognitive science
- Published research outputs in peer-reviewed rejournals

Predictive Analytics Data Fellow

June - August 2021

Centre for Humanitarian Data, United Nations

Focus area: Predictive Modeling, Complex Systems; Data-Driven Policy-Making Key achievements

- Identified methods, data requirements, and partnerships for a pilot on data-driven cholera response
- Provided strategic recommendations on introducing causal modeling into humanitarian needs assessment
- Disseminated findings through a technical report, a blog post, conference talks, and webinars

Education

PhD, Cognitive Neuroscience September 2016 - October 2019 Aarhus University, Denmark

MSc, Cognitive Science (Focus: Computational Linguistics)

September 2014 - July 2016 University of Trento, Italy

Additional research experience

Visiting Researcher, Department of Applied Mathematics and Computer Science; Technical University of Denmark, 2018-19
Visiting Researcher, Institute of Cognitive Science and Technologies; National Research Council, Italy, 2018
Research Assistant, Department of Experimental Psychology, University College London, United Kingdom, 2016
Research Assistant, Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics, Nijmegen, The Netherlands, 2015-16

Publications

In preparation and under review

- Rocca, R., Yarkoni, T. (under review), Language as a fingerprint: A self-supervised approach to text-based user modeling using transformers

CV - Roberta Rocca 1/3

- Hansen, L., Rocca, R., Fusaroli, R. (in preparation), A multi-modal, multi-diagnostic approach to language-based inference of mental disorders
- Rocca. R., Tamagnone, N., Contla, X., Bove, J.B., Rekab-saz, N. (in preparation), Natural language processing for humanitarian action: challenges, opportunities, and the path towards a humanitarian NLP community
- Rocca, R., de la Vega, A. (under review), Evaluating the role of non-lexical markers in LLMs' language modeling behavior

First-author papers in peer-reviewed journals

- de la Vega, A.*, Rocca, R.* (co-first), Blair, R., Mentch, J., Markiewicz, C., Ghosh, S., Poldrack, R., Yarkoni, T. (2022), Neuroscout: a unified platform for generalized and reproducible fMRI research, eLife
- Rocca, R., Yarkoni, T. (2021). Putting psychology to the test: rethinking model evaluation through benchmarking and prediction, Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science
- Rocca, R., Coventry, K. R., Tylén, K., Staib, M., Lund, T. E., & Wallentin, M. (2020). Language beyond the language system: dorsal visuospatial pathways support processing of demonstratives and spatial language during naturalistic fast fMRI, NeuroImage
- Rocca, R., Wallentin, M. (2020). Demonstrative reference and semantic space: a large-scale demonstrative choice task (DCT) study. Frontiers in Psychology
- Rocca, R., Wallentin, M., Vesper, C., & Tylén, K. (2019). This is for you: social modulations of proximal vs. distal space in collaborative interaction, *Scientific Reports*
- Rocca, R., Tylén, K., Wallentin, M. (2019), *This* shoe, *that* tiger: Semantic properties reflecting manual affordances of the referent modulate demonstratives use, *PlosOne*

Other papers in peer-reviewed journals

- Todisco, E., Rocca, R., Wallentin, M. (2021). The semantics of spatial demonstratives in Spanish: a demonstrative choice task study. *Language and Cognition*
- Wallentin, M., Rocca, R., Stoustrup S. (2019), Grammar, gender and demonstratives in lateralized imagery for sentences, *Journal of Psycholinguistic Research*
- Carapezza, M., & Rocca, R. (2017). In-seguire la Regola: Giochi Linguistici e Arti Performative. Rivista Italiana di Filosofia del Linguaggio, 11(2) (in Italian)

Papers in peer-reviewed conference proceedings

- Rocca R., Tylén, K. (2022), Cognitive diversity promotes collective creativity: an agent-based simulation, Proceedings of the 44th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society
- Wallentin, M., Rocca, R. (2020). The semantics of spatial demonstratives. Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society
- Rocca, R., Wallentin, M., Vesper, C. & Tylén, K. (2018). This and that back in context: grounding demonstrative reference in manual and social affordances, Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society
- Wallentin, M., Rocca, R., Stoustrup, S. (2018), Lateralized imagery for sentence content: Testing grammar, gender and demonstratives, *Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society*

Technical reports

- Rocca, R., (2021) Complex Systems Modeling for Humanitarian Action: Methods and Opportunities, Research Report for the United Nations' Centre for Humanitarian Data, pdf available here

Articles in newspapers and magazines (in Italian)

- Algoritmi di classe, *Doppiozero*, available <u>here</u>
- Chi ha paura dei data scientists? Numeri e pandemia, Doppiozero, available here
- Dati, miti, stati, L'identità di Clio, available here

Open-source contributions

Since 2019, I have been part of team developing Neuroscout: https://neuroscout.org, a fully open-source unified platform for the analysis of naturalistic neuroimaging data. A overview of the platform and its applications can be found in our recent *eLife* paper: https://elifesciences.org/articles/79277.

I am one of the main contributors and maintainers of the open-source feature extraction library *pliers* https://github.com/PsychoinformaticsLab/pliers, which is used by Neuroscout to extract visual, auditory and linguistic features from naturalistic fMRI stimuli.

CV - Roberta Rocca 2/3

I am co-first author of the Neuroscout release paper mentioned above, and I contributed to designing and executing the meta-analytic validation studies presented there. We shared all the underlying code in this GitHub repository: https://github.com/neuroscout/neuroscout-paper, which is also available as a fully executable Jupyter book: https://neuroscout.github.io/neuroscout-paper/intro.html.

Code for analyses reported on my publications is shared on GitHub. As an example, this repository: https://github.com/rbroc/benchmarks paper contains the code for Rocca & Yarkoni (2022), "Putting psychology to the test: rethinking model evaluation through benchmarking and prediction", published on Advances in Methods and Practices for Psychological Science.

You can check my GitHub profiles for more examples of open-source code related to ongoing projects. For data protection reasons, code and data for projects using clinical data is stored in private repositories.

Presentations, teaching and outreach

I have taught university courses in Statistical Methods (BSc in Cognitive Science), R Programming (Staff course at Aarhus University), Foundations of Cognitive Science (MA in Cognitive Semiotics), Cognitive Neuroscience (BSc and MSC in Cognitive Science); Social and Cultural Dynamics (BSc in Cognitive Science)

I have presented my work at (among other venues): the Annual Meeting of the Organization for Human Brain Mapping (Rome, 2019; Glasgow, 2022); the Annual Conference of the Society for the Neurobiology of Language (Québec City, 2018; Helsinki, 2019); the Annual Meeting Cognitive Science Society (Madison - WI, 2018; Online, 2020; Toronto/Hybrid, 2022), the Conference of the Society for Complex Systems (Lyon/Hybrid, 2021). I have been invited to present my work at seminar series held by McGill University, Karolinska Institute and University of Toronto, and at the Centre for Humanitarian Data.

In 2019, I organized a workshop on Natural Language Processing at Aarhus University, bringing together academic experts in the field from several countries.

Other interests

When I am not doing science, I play bass in a band, write fiction, and watch art-house movies. I really enjoy learning new languages, and I am counting on expanding my current repertoire. I spend most of my holiday time going on high-stamina road trips and long hikes.

CV - Roberta Rocca 3/3